Benjamin Houghton: Hey? Hello, so if you can't tell, this video is gonna be about modern Cnn architectures.
Benjamin Houghton: And so we should talk about that real fast kind of what do I mean by that? So we know now, or we should know now what a
Benjamin Houghton: a simple vanilla Cnn architecture is, right where? What's my? The square to represent a convolutional layer? And we might take that. And
Benjamin Houghton: we might do some type of batch normalization before, and then maybe apply a relu function
Benjamin Houghton: after that. Right? We said we might do a really function as an activation function. But essentially, we just keep
Benjamin Houghton: taking the output of one convolutional layer, and then it's plugging in into the next. And finally, maybe we we flatten it right, which is often depicted as like a long skinny line where we've taken a an image of many channels. And we've unraveled it into a single vector of
Benjamin Houghton: a single vector with with
Benjamin Houghton: which is no longer in the shape of a matrix or a tensor. And then now we can. We can feed it into a dense like feedboard network, right? Which we often did take with these little circles. And then we can do some, maybe some type of classification tasks, right? So we might put this into a sigma function? Something like that, right? Or we might do a multi class classification or a number of different tasks. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: but this is what we would consider a a very basic or a vanilla implementation of a a
Benjamin Houghton: convolutional neural network. And so today we're going to talk about is really more modern approaches. Right? So building upon the basic idea of a convolutional neural network into more and more advanced architectures. And what we're going to see today, really, too, is that these modern architectures, while they're each have their own novel architecture.
Benjamin Houghton: What's maybe more important is the idea that they introduce. And so I can give you like a very quick example of that is is resnet right? So resnet
Benjamin Houghton: interest. The introduces the idea of residual connections, and
Benjamin Houghton: which we will talk more in depth about here shortly. But a residual connection is used in in
Benjamin Houghton: can be used really in any convolutional neural network. It's not limited to just the resnet architecture per se, right? So that's kind of what's unique about
Benjamin Houghton: about these architectures, and is that we can kind of mix and match and and use
Benjamin Houghton: the ideas that they introduce in in various.
Benjamin Houghton: we can, we can introduce. We can use them in various architectures, in, in different types of models. Even right? So the idea of a residual connection is used not only in convolutional networks, but also things like transformers. So typically in modern deep learning.
Benjamin Houghton: You're gonna use a number of ideas from a number of of these, a number of these ideas that were introduced here today.
Benjamin Houghton: So let's get right into it, then. Oh, so let me erase this.
Benjamin Houghton: So
Benjamin Houghton: traditional Cnn's face a a vanishing gradient problem. So that's 1 of the things that we're going to talk about today. And and modern architectures introduce innovations overcome these limitations. Okay, so
Benjamin Houghton: not only do they face a granishing gradient problem as depth increases. But really what they should also say here is that
Benjamin Houghton: that
Benjamin Houghton: the information, like in A and like we saw on the previous slide. The example, where the data goes kind of sequentially like this. Right? Well, this operation down here, this convolution doesn't really see what happens, what? What this input look like, because it gets filtered here by this convolution. So the data has been
Benjamin Houghton: transformed, in a sense. And so it doesn't really see the whole picture. And that's another idea that you know the information doesn't flow as well when you when you filter. It's it's kind of like Simon says, when we're all sitting in, we all sit in a circle, you know, and we we whisper each person whispers a sentence to, or a word to the person next to them, by the time it gets back around, what originally was said might be very different.
Benjamin Houghton: so that's kind of one of the problems that traditional Cnn's face as well in in addition, and it kind of goes hand in hand with the vanishing gradient problem. If the information can't flow easily for backward. There's it also can't probably flow very easily forward, right? Or vice versa.
Benjamin Houghton: So let's see.
Benjamin Houghton: yeah. So Vgg, we'll talk about this. But really they're small. Convolutional filters was was kind of. And this is like a broad overview. Right? So we'll talk more about these in depth. So don't worry about if you don't understand what what these things mean. But I was saying previously that each one of these models, or each one of these these modern architectures kind of introduces a new idea that we can use to build better and better models. And we can use all these ideas together, which, in fact, which
Benjamin Houghton: we'll see that kind of how this kind of plays out.
Benjamin Houghton: But
Benjamin Houghton: we have these, they say small. By small small filters they mean what they mean. Here is 3 by 3 kernels. Resnet uses shortcut or skip connections right? So we'll talk about that where the information can flow this way, but it also
Benjamin Houghton: right. Well, I kind of ran out of room. Here, let me let me draw my drawing down here, where the information kind of flows this way right?
Benjamin Houghton: But it also is gonna flow this way. Right? Okay? So that's the idea of residual connections, or or shortcuts dense net. I'm not going to try and draw that here because we have diagrams later on. But essentially, with the dense connections. It's kind of like interconnecting the network more. It. It kind of starts to look
Benjamin Houghton: if I had to describe it. It sort of looks like at least describe it in few words. It kind of looks like a dense layer would, except for convolutions. So everything's kind of interconnected in a sense. And then, lastly, we'll talk about mobile net.
Benjamin Houghton: And it's idea of you know these depth wise? It's major contribution. Is these depth wise, separable convolutions which are supposed to be much more efficient than like a traditional like it's gonna be than a traditional convolution that you're used to seeing. And we'll talk about that. And what that means.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright.
Benjamin Houghton: So let's talk about Bgg first.st
Benjamin Houghton: because it is the 1st architecture that's and you know these are kind of in in order of the way they were introduced. Timeline wise and see, here's the a link here to the paper.
Benjamin Houghton: If you want to read about it. But we will probably take a look at that here in a little bit. But for the time being
Benjamin Houghton: let's we'll we'll just take a look. What's here on the slide. So it is a
Benjamin Houghton: the. It was a neural network design for image classification task, and and I probably should have said this right off that. But you know, I pick we picked these specific models right the Bgg resnet, dense net mobilenet. But I mean there are many, many more, and especially when we start talking about different types of tasks. So really, we're focused on classification tasks. I mean.
Benjamin Houghton: these ideas like residual connections. I said, not only gets used in other type of Cnn architecture, but even other types of models like transformers and and feed forward whatever type of model almost you can think of, you can almost always implement a residual connection. Right? You're just kind of bypassing a layer essentially. So.
Benjamin Houghton: however, you know, these models were kind of all designed with the idea of image classification, and or they were measured up against image classification. Right? So when these papers are written, they might they all compared against what's something called imagenet, which?
Benjamin Houghton: right, like they all use. This is a massive data set where they all classified images from image set, and that's how they kind of compared, vgg, you know, because Vgg wrote their paper and then Resnet said, Hey, like we did the same thing resnet or vggj, we used Imagenet. And here's how we did. So. It's kind of like the benchmark, and that's why. You see, you know, that's the benchmark is these classification tasks? Okay? So now that's out of the way.
Benjamin Houghton: let's see, this was developed by the visual geometry group at Oxford. Okay, neat. It's demonstrated effectiveness, effectiveness of deep networks with uniform architecture. Right? And they really, this is the big thing here. This is what they pioneered is these 3 by 3 stack on top of each other kernels. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: And so what? What does that mean?
Benjamin Houghton: well, it's just like a normal convolution that you've you've probably seen before.
Benjamin Houghton: where the kernels kind of look like something down here. Right? So down here we have a a normal kernel like it's. This is like a 3 by 3 kernel. Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: And down here at the bottom. Left this blue 1, 3 by 3 kernel
Benjamin Houghton: and then. Now we are going to add input channel, right? So now we have a 3 by 3 by 3 filter. So if you're filtering 3 channels, you know this, this now becomes a filter, right? This filter is made up of 3 kernels.
Benjamin Houghton: Each kernel has its own respective input channel that it is responsible for. So maybe the red one's responsible for the red channel, the green and then the blue channel for maybe it's an RGB image as an input right
Benjamin Houghton: and then. So this will have 3 input channels, and this also will have. And this particular filter will produce one single output channel. Right? So now. Now we look at over here on the right. Now we have a group of filters, right? So here we have 6 by 3 by 3 filters, and the depth here is sick, and there's 3 of them.
Benjamin Houghton: So we have. It should be actually 3 by you could think of it as 3 by 6, by 3, by 3. Right? So we have 3 filters. They each have 6
Benjamin Houghton: input channels, and they have 3 by 3 kernels. And so what this means is that now these 3 filters are each gonna produce their own output channel. But
Benjamin Houghton: and they they take in 6 input channels as we see like there's a red channel, green, blue, yellow, purple, orange. I don't think of them as colors right like, you know. Colors don't mean anything right like
Benjamin Houghton: each channel. Essentially, you could think of it as gray scale. Because it's a single Val. It's a, it's just each input. Channel is just a 2 dimensional matrix, right? There's no concept of color, just intensity. Which we should, we should talk about that during right? We talked about that during the image data.
Benjamin Houghton: But the idea here is that this is the idea of like these, these stacked kernels. Right? So you have these stacked 3 by 3 kernels. And this is what the Vgg architecture does. And this is kind of similar. You know, this is essentially, you know it. This is still kind of a vanilla convolutional. I mean, I will say it is a vanilla convolutional neural network, right? It is just we're gonna do. We'll see here in a minute. But we're just gonna do these 3 by 3
Benjamin Houghton: convolutions over and over again. And you know, we'll do batch normalization. And of course, relu activation functions between each convolutional layer. But essentially, we're just stacking them on top of each other and
Benjamin Houghton: doing it over and over again, right? And and that's kind of what you're used to seeing. But it's important to start with Bgg, because this is kind of where it all starts right. This is where the the like. The modern Cnn. Architecture was kind of born, so to speak.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright. So what is a Vgg architecture? Let's talk about a little more in depth, right? So there's different ones. Right? So 16 is often
Benjamin Houghton: used for
Benjamin Houghton: I guess, for demonstration purposes or examples. It's a very. It's pretty common one to use. But there's other ones like. So we have. Vgg. 16, which has 16 layers. And obviously we have 1113 and 19, with their respective number of layers. The input, image is, this is
Benjamin Houghton: this is kind of not important to know. Well, it is kind of important to know, I guess. You should definitely know what size your images need to be in order to use these models. Right? So actually, we'll see this
Benjamin Houghton: and the other models as well resnet and dense net. They all use the same input size of
Benjamin Houghton: 3 by 2, 2, 4 by. And you'll actually a lot of times you'll see this written as 2, 2, 4 by 2, 2, 4 by 3, and almost all the literature. I refuse to use that notation, because that is not the way we do it in deep learning and apply torch. The 3 is always at the front, right? So 3 input channels. So this means 3 input channels, you know, and then
Benjamin Houghton: then we have 2 2 with by height. And if you you know, I'll just say I'm gonna be consistent. Almost always. And so I'm always gonna list
Benjamin Houghton: the number of examples. So like, N, right? So we have n training examples by the number of channels. Let's say we have 3 channels, and the image height is 2 24 by 2 24. Right? I'm always going to use this notation, because this is what the way your data needs to be structured when you feed it into a neural network. So I don't know
Benjamin Houghton: I don't. I don't know why I would put the channels at the end. I mean, that's the way like nump. I guess you know, data is often packaged that way. Like. If you open up. If you go to plot an image in like matplot live, or something, it'll complain at the Channel layer. It's not hard, right? It's like one line of code to move the Channel dimension to the back. But it just be aware of that right like in deep learning. We like to have the Channel dimension at the front right? Because
Benjamin Houghton: the channels are independent, right? Like the green channel for image data. I guess they kind of like. They all, in a sense, work together. But as soon as we start feeding these things through models and networks, each channel is its own identity, right? Like they shouldn't be mixed together. So to me it makes more sense to have it at the end or at the front, and that's the way Pytorch wants it. And that's it's more efficient for for the computations. And so that's the way it's it's done. And so
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, moving on. We've talked enough about the order of the dimensions. Let's see. So right?
Benjamin Houghton: convolutional layers. 13 layers right?
Benjamin Houghton: 3 by 3 filters. We already talked about that. And then there's a there'll be a Max pooling operation after the convolutional error to reduce the dimensionality. That's kind of misleading sentence in the sense. Because
Benjamin Houghton: yes, you're reducing the dimensionality. But you're typically when you do, a polling operation is because you increase the number of channels. And actually, what the Vg architecture does. Is it kind of maintains the same computate number of computations? Right? So it might go from 32 to 64 channels. But it's gonna reduce image size, say, from 56
Benjamin Houghton: to to 20. Let's see, actually, what is. We'll look here in a minute. But maybe it's not a good example, I don't remember exactly the image size, but it basically cuts it in half. So actually, I do know. For a fact, it goes from 1 12 to 56. Okay, it goes from 2, 2, 4 down to 1, 12 down to 56. So every time it doubles the number of channels, it's gonna you typically reduce the image size dimensions by half. And so that kind of
Benjamin Houghton: in a sense maintains the same.
Benjamin Houghton: it maintains the same amount of computations. That's part of this architecture that they introduced. Okay? And then, finally, yeah, we have fully connected layers at the end, that flatten it and then, like, we might have a number of them. So here they use 3 fully connected layers. And then, yeah, output is softmax activation for multi class application. Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: yeah. And then the output size. Right? So it's probably important to know this. I mean, you can change this whatever you want, right? Like, typically you would use the the Cnn architecture, and then your last, your final, your output layer, your fully connected layer would be, whatever your batch size you want, but it would be
Benjamin Houghton: designed to, you know, you would have so many output nodes. So here's a thousand, because there's a thousand classes in image net. But if you had 3 classes, you know, then you would just have it'd be batch size by 3, or if you had 64 classes it'd be batch size by 64. Whatever number of classes you have. Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: Okay? So
Benjamin Houghton: let's see, I think here in the next. Yeah, the next is our diagram of Vgg architecture, and again, like you should be pretty used to seeing this if you're used to convolutional neural neural networks. This really shouldn't be anything new to you. Right? So here we have the I've listed here the dimensions of I think this yeah, this would be.
Benjamin Houghton: Oh, we'll look here in a minute at the different configurations. But I pretty sure this would be like Bgg. 16, maybe. I'm not sure it not sure. But I'm not sure it really matters. But
Benjamin Houghton: We'll we'll he'll we'll know here in a second. So again, like we have the
Benjamin Houghton: the 1st block right?
Benjamin Houghton: Where? Actually, let's take a look real fast at this.
Benjamin Houghton: Right here.
Benjamin Houghton: Good. Yeah. Actually, I think I need to. I need to fix this right? So
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, the input is actually 3. That's just a typo. I apologize. This is should be right, should be 3,
Benjamin Houghton: by 2, 2, 4 by by 2, 2, 4, okay, so it's 3 channels. Input and but yes, this is 3.
Benjamin Houghton: Write that, 3 by 2, 2, 4 by 2, 2, 4, input, okay, and the output is is 64 by 1, 12 by 1 12. And we see that they always there's basically
Benjamin Houghton: 3 by 3 convolution rate loop, 3 by 3 convolution rate loop, Max pooling right? And then we go to the next layer. We go to the next block, and the block has
Benjamin Houghton: 2 convolutional layers and a Max pooling, and and it does the same thing where 128 filters 128 filters 100. And so we've gone from 64 filters to our 64 channels to 128. So guess what we're gonna do. We're gonna use Max pooling and reduce the image size by in half. Right? So the next layer right, 1 28 we have 128 filters now, as the input. And the image size, you know, is 64, right? So we actually, it's written right here.
Benjamin Houghton: so we see that 64 to 128
Benjamin Houghton: fill a number of channels, and the
Benjamin Houghton: image size has been cut in half. Okay? And so that pattern continues throughout the entire the entire
Benjamin Houghton: model. And then, finally, we we do like a fully connected layer here at the end. We we take the output of the final layer. We flatten it and run through a couple of fully connected layers and and do some type of soft Mac, do a soft Max activation and to get our our prediction, our our class predictions.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, so let's take a look at this. Now, we've seen architecture. We'd probably be able to read this a little bit better. So this comes directly from the Btg paper. You can click on this link, and it'll take you to this table here. But let's look at this 16 layer, right? So
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, see? Before I said, the input was actually just to show you what I was talking about. So here, block one, the input is, should this should be, this should be read 3 by 2, 2, 4, right? Right?
Benjamin Houghton: And the actually, you see that right here. So the input here for 16 layers is 3 by 2, 2, 4 by 2, 2, 4. We have 2 convolutions, a Max pooling. Then we have 2 convolutions, a Max pooling. We have 2 convolutions, and then a 1 dimensional convolution.
Benjamin Houghton: oh, yeah, or this, there's 2 different versions, right? So there's a single convolution. And there's like the the 3 convolution version, right? So actually. And looking at this, looking at this model now. And I just realized this is not the bg, 16, right? This would be
Benjamin Houghton: oh, no, it would actually, because I need to update this graphic. I apologize. I will do that.
Benjamin Houghton: But you can see. I just need to. Actually, if you look at this diagram right, you'll see there's 2 blue box, 2 blue boxes right, and then a red, 2 yellow, and then a red, 3 purple, and then a red, which means it should have been 3,
Benjamin Houghton: 3, 3 by 3 convolutions. So this is actually, the Bgc 16 architecture. I just didn't update here on this slide. I need to add another bullet point and say, and I apologize because this is a brand new diagram. So I'll update that but this needs to say,
Benjamin Houghton: here show you exactly where.
Benjamin Houghton: So here there needs to be another 3 by 3.
Benjamin Houghton: Here there needs to be another 3 by 3, and here there needs to be
Benjamin Houghton: another 3 by 3. So the orange block, the green block and the purple blocks. Okay, the yellow and the blue are
Benjamin Houghton: or 2. There's just 2 convolution like. And then, anyways, that's that's kind of not super important, and these could also be one by one, right now that you've seen the architecture, the idea is that you can kind of read this for yourself. And you understand, like what this table means, because at 1st it's kind of kind of hard to understand what they're what they're trying to say right and we know that there's a ray lou activation after each convolution layer. Okay,
Benjamin Houghton: right? So. And then we can see down here. I guess this is kind of important it'll factor in later. But we can see the different number of parameters for for the network, right? We see that it obviously grows as we add more layers. And it's quite a few.
Benjamin Houghton: quite a few parameters. I think, though, what is not clear here is that
Benjamin Houghton: maybe we'll take a look here at the paper. But
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, let's do that real fast,
Benjamin Houghton: I think. Yeah. So the the Va. The vast majority of these parameters are from
Benjamin Houghton: these linear layers. Right? So
Benjamin Houghton: not sure if it mentions it here. But I can almost guarantee it is. Yeah, that's a massive like these 4 96 layers, or that's like a massive amount of parameters. Right? So let's so we can do a quick calculation right? So just to
Benjamin Houghton: just to my calculator go from
Benjamin Houghton: the 1st
Benjamin Houghton: fully connected to the other. So if there's 496 output nodes, and there's 496 input nodes. Let's see, each node is gonna have a parameter for each output. Right? So that's 4 96. Guess what times 4 96 is. Yeah, it's
Benjamin Houghton: it's 16 million parameters.
Benjamin Houghton: And so let's see. And then also I would have to see what the size
Benjamin Houghton: I'd have to see what the size of this output layer is but
Benjamin Houghton: the dimensionality of it. So let's see. So the output layer
Benjamin Houghton: 512 channels. Let's see, let's see, let's take a look at.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, here they're just talking about. They're explaining why the 3 by 3 convolutions are way, less number of parameters than the 7 by 7, which was more common before this paper to use 7 by 7.
Benjamin Houghton: let's go back to are notes here and take a look.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? So this output.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah. So the input is, yeah, it's big. 5, 12 by 7 by 7. That's the size of the
Benjamin Houghton: the file image, right? The file.
Benjamin Houghton: right? So 512, 5, 7
Benjamin Houghton: times 7 is like 25,000
Benjamin Houghton: 25,000 pixels, essentially right, because you have 512, 7 by 7 images.
Benjamin Houghton: And if we multiply that number by 4,096, you see. Yeah, it's there you go there. There's those are all the parameters, right? 100 and 2 million, and it's kind of silly, I mean.
Benjamin Houghton: maybe they do talk about it in this paper, but I I don't remember now, but I knew that when I saw that I I felt like it was kind of silly, that
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, a hundred 2. They're they're they're saying, oh, there's this many millions parameters, but they they neglect
Benjamin Houghton: to say that they go like, I can say that a hundred. But basically, you know, what is that? Like 80% of them or more, whatever it is is from these linear layers. Like, what? Yeah? So I mean.
Benjamin Houghton: anyways, so let's yeah, let's move on
Benjamin Houghton: to. That's that's it. That's really, that's Bgg, right? So it's basically
Benjamin Houghton: you could think of it as
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, basically a very deep, large version of
Benjamin Houghton: of like what you're used to seeing in convolutional neural network. And this is kind of like I said before, is the modern, where the modern and architecture is born. And this is kind of what we'll build from. This is this this version. And yeah, we'll talk later on about why, Bgg, I mean, I mean, like, I said, it's
Benjamin Houghton: we'll talk about, you know why it's important and why we're talking about it. But you know
Benjamin Houghton: know that it's kind of like the starting point. We had to start somewhere. And this is where we start right? So and that's kind of and resonance gonna build off and and resident is extremely important architecture to understand. Luckily, it's really pretty simple to understand. So resident, introduce this idea of residual learning.
Benjamin Houghton: and the idea is that
Benjamin Houghton: they enable the training of very deep networks without without vanishing gradients. Okay, so again, like, it's not just about the vanishing gradients. It's also about information flow right? It's so. One layer can see what you know. If one layer filters something and completely distorts it. The next layer has no idea what the original input looked like. Right? So it gets some. I get some sense of what it looked like through these this residual connection. Alright and it.
Benjamin Houghton: And
Benjamin Houghton: you know what's maybe we should talk about this real fast, about what like, how it helps with the Spanish ingredient effect. Right? So right? So if you know.
Benjamin Houghton: let's say we have. X,
Benjamin Houghton: goes into 3 convolutional layers right? And we'll call this h 1. Call this h, 2, and this h, 3, right? And then, you know, this goes into some loss function, right? And
Benjamin Houghton: we want to know, what do we want to know. We want to know the gradient of X with respect to, or the gradient about the loss or the call, you know. Usually we do this with respect to the cost. If if you, if you guys have taken the deep learning, you know that
Benjamin Houghton: we we care about the cost. But you know. Here we'll just. We'll just use the loss. Right for simplicity.
Benjamin Houghton: we don't want to know what the gradient of of the losses with respect to X. Okay, so how do we do that? Well, we know from the chain rule.
Benjamin Houghton: Essentially, we need to do the gradient of bad
Benjamin Houghton: little loss with respect to base 3
Benjamin Houghton: times the gradient of L. With respect to H. 2 times the gradient
Benjamin Houghton: FH. 1. 0, I'm sorry.
Benjamin Houghton: Oh, let me rewrite that got ahead of myself.
Benjamin Houghton: This actually going to be the gradient.
Benjamin Houghton: H. 3
Benjamin Houghton: time. With respect to lost times. Now we do the gradient of H. 3 with respect to H. 2 times the gradient of
Benjamin Houghton: h 2 with respect to h. 1, and then finally, we can do the gradient, and then that'll tell us.
Benjamin Houghton: you know, we multiply by the gradient of X with respect to h. 1. And then this will finally tell us, like, what this is equal to right, that's weird. So we take, you know. And so obviously, if these numbers are like, you know, 0 point I I know these are tensors. But let's just say it's a scalar, right? For some reason.
Benjamin Houghton: 0 point 5 times 0 point 1 times 0 point 3 times. I don't know negative 0 point 5 like, you can see that we multiply these fractions together. Eventually, these gradients are going to become
Benjamin Houghton: very, very small. And so as we move backwards through the network the gradients essentially go to 0 and
Benjamin Houghton: Now, if we use a residual connection, however.
Benjamin Houghton: you know it, it changes all this right because we know that.
Benjamin Houghton: Let's say Z is equal to x plus F of x right?
Benjamin Houghton: And then that means that even if let's say, F of X is just
Benjamin Houghton: Let's say the gradient.
Benjamin Houghton: The derivative F of X is like, really small number, right? Like, it's 0 point.
Benjamin Houghton: right? It's like 0 point 1 or something like that, right? So now, if this term so if this was well, yeah, let's do it like this.
Benjamin Houghton: Don't really have a lot of room here. I apologize. Let me erase all this.
Benjamin Houghton: But what was I saying? So what I was saying was, if
Benjamin Houghton: Z is equal to F of X, okay.
Benjamin Houghton: and we want to know what the derivative of Z is, or with respect to X, then
Benjamin Houghton: right? It's her. Yeah, which is just here. It's just a derivative of
Benjamin Houghton: just the root of F of X, and let's say, that's a small number like 0 point 1. Right? So that's a pretty small like, you know, as we chain these together, right? We saw on a previous example, like, if we do this over and over again, like these numbers can get really small. But let's now say that Z is actually equal to F of x
Benjamin Houghton: plus x, right? So now it doesn't matter what like if this F of X could be essentially 0. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: we, the gradient is still gonna flow back through the network to x, because the the derivative here of
Benjamin Houghton: of X is is one. Right? So if oh, I don't know which happens. Had a technical ipad disconnected there, it's back. Okay. So if
Benjamin Houghton: this, if this was 0. If the group, if the derivative, like the derivative console.
Benjamin Houghton: there we go pencil.
Benjamin Houghton: So now the
Benjamin Houghton: derivative of Z with respect to x right or the partial of Z. With respect to X.
Benjamin Houghton: What's this would be 0 plus one, right? So you know, the gradient a Z is gonna flow. The upstream gradient is gonna flow fully back through through the network here. And and so that's what we mean. That's why these these addition
Benjamin Houghton: matters. And that's literally what these residual connections are. I guess I should have mentioned that before I drew all this down here.
Benjamin Houghton: But
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, you see here, residual connection is is it's written here. It's F of x plus x. So when we say, add you literally just add to get them together. So we have 2 matrices.
Benjamin Houghton: 2 images, and we literally add them together. So this could be like this, 1, 2, 3, 4 is one image, or 2 by 2 image. And this image is 1, 1 1. Yeah, we're literally just gonna add them together. It's going to be one, or I'm sorry. 2, 3, okay, you get the idea and not enough room on the slide to to do this. So
Benjamin Houghton: so but
Benjamin Houghton: let me do it on here. So 1, 2, 3, a little better example. Right? And let's say, this is one.
Benjamin Houghton: negative, 1, 2 0. Okay? So then this is gonna be equal to right, it's just like in place. And just so I and I know this is simple math guys, right? Obviously, it's just doing this. So there's no
Benjamin Houghton: cause. When I 1st saw this I thought it was kind of odd. I was like, what do you mean? Just add, and they literally just add them together right? So one plus 1, 2, minus 1, 3 plus 2 and 0 plus 4, right? So that's what a residual connection is. And this allows the gradient to to bypass essentially a layer that has a really small derivative, essentially, or a really small gradient. Okay,
Benjamin Houghton: and so yeah, it it did really well on image net like I said, this is the benchmark. It'd be, you know, compared to Bgg and their previous architectures. And you know, obviously, it's you can use a pre trained model, and
Benjamin Houghton: for other fines for other tasks. So Resnet gets used a lot. You know, you might use like a pre trained model for and and then you just tune it to your specific app that was trained. Usually. Maybe it's trained on the image net, and then you just fine tune it for your application. Let's see, it's effective training. Yeah, it. Yeah, we. We know that approved gradient flow. And it definitely
Benjamin Houghton: lasting influence, absolutely lasting influence on modern architectures, for sure. Capable of very deep networks. Right? So
Benjamin Houghton: we see, yeah, resnet 50. Yeah, we now we're 50 layers right. Bgg was like what 19 was the deepest one or something like that. And now we have
Benjamin Houghton: a hundred, and up to 152 layers, and and really, I mean
Benjamin Houghton: I I don't. We'll see. You can look at the results of their paper. I don't know if it there's a this diminishing returns with resnet. So it might not pay to go deeper than that. And you know you start talking about computational efficiency and stuff like that. But
Benjamin Houghton: the idea is that it doesn't really matter how many layers you have, because with this skip connection the gradient can always flow backwards, because the no matter what F, no matter what the derivative of F of x is the the gradient right or the let's see, the derivative of H of X is always, always going to be
Benjamin Houghton: one
Benjamin Houghton: right? It's always going to be. With respect to X, it's always going to be the gradient right, the derivative of F
Benjamin Houghton: plus one. This is always going to be one. So it doesn't matter what this number is over here. Okay, so
Benjamin Houghton: it, it's all it. Yeah, it. So anyways, it doesn't matter how deep the network gets for that reason.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? So let's talk about a little bit more about, you know, we talked about what a residual block looks like. And actually, maybe we should take a closer look at that diagram before we move forward. But yeah. So
Benjamin Houghton: 3 by 3. Convolution. Okay.
Benjamin Houghton: which? Guess what? That came from? Bgg, alright, we have our input images, which is batch by channel by height, by width. Okay.
Benjamin Houghton: fashion normalization. All right, Raylu operation. All right.
Benjamin Houghton: Another convolution batch normalization. Add add the residual connection. And then a relu operation. So I mean, that's it. Like it's it's all pretty.
Benjamin Houghton: It's all stuff you've seen before. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: If you're familiar with convolutional neural networks, you you definitely. This is nothing new. You're just adding this residual connection.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: So let's see here, residual blocks. Yeah, incorporate to skip connections that include gradient flow, right? Batch, normalization stabilizes. Right? So you're always, always going to use batch normalization. I know we haven't talked about it much today.
Benjamin Houghton: You're pretty much, always going to want to use batch normal, some type of normalization with these convolutional neural networks. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: the this input again, like, you know, you could write your own model like you could make your own version of resnet.
Benjamin Houghton: But the standard architecture is takes this the size images you need to get your images into this shape. If you're going to use like a pre-trained model or something like that. Convolutional layers pose multiple residual blocks. Right? Right? So we have multiple. Each layer has multiple of these these little blocks. We saw this. So here's residual block. So we have multiple residual blocks, makes up a layer. And then we might have multiple layers, makes up, makes up a whole model.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay? And then finally, again, like, we have the fully connected layers at the end where
Benjamin Houghton: we do actually, yeah, we do some type of global average pooling which which is followed by fully connected layer. Right? So I think in, I didn't mention this before.
Benjamin Houghton: Max, yeah. So that's 1 of the things that is kind of.
Benjamin Houghton: I believe. Yeah. And that's kind of I think that was I. I guess I should have mentioned this before. So unlike Bgg, which just
Benjamin Houghton: just flattens the final layer. Right? I think.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, that's a big difference. Right? So here we'll see this here in a minute.
Benjamin Houghton: we use some type of global pooling to to get the essentially, that's how we flatten this right because we have to go from image data, you know, multiple 3 dimensional tensors
Benjamin Houghton: to single dimension. And you know, or, yeah, I guess that would be yeah. One dimensional vectors, right?
Benjamin Houghton: And then we do our classification for Imagenet with our
Benjamin Houghton: output size of 1,000 batch size by 1,000. Okay, alright. So here is.
Benjamin Houghton: This is from again like this is from the paper. So take a closer look at this. This links to the diagram, but the solid arrows indicate residual connections. Oh, I'm sorry. Wait.
Benjamin Houghton: No, this should say, dashed, oh, it does. Okay. Yeah. Solid arrows indicate.
Benjamin Houghton: Oh, I'm sorry it does. Yeah. What am I talking about? Sorry. Yes, my notes are correct. Solid arrows indicate residual connections. The dashed arrow represents residual connections with a 1 by one convolution and stride of 2 for down sampling right? So on like Bgg, where we do like the
Benjamin Houghton: Max pooling, you'll see that there is no Max pooling in in res that actually right? So there is at the beginning. Here. There's this pooling layer.
Benjamin Houghton: But other than that, that's how they were. They actually they reduced the image sizes. Right? So we'll talk more about the dimensions here. Yeah, on the resnet configuration slide the over, and the divided by 2 symbol indicates a stride of 2, usually for convolutions, but also for pooling operations. Right? So if you look at this diagram, you'll see a bunch of places where like, right here, for example, where it says over 2
Benjamin Houghton: over 2 over to
Benjamin Houghton: And so that just means a stride of 2
Benjamin Houghton: in the paper. They say, the down sampling is formed directly by convolutional layers that have a stride up to right? So
Benjamin Houghton: right? So, okay, so let's kind of unpack that right. So
Benjamin Houghton: when we go from purple to green
Benjamin Houghton: right, we're going to down sample. So we're going from 64 channels to 128 in order to do that, we use a stride of 2 right, and the stride of 2 reduces. The image cuts the image size in half. But there's also this residual connection, right? So like, when we add these images together, right?
Benjamin Houghton: Which is going to be like this, we can't add this big image to this little image. They have to be the same dimensions, right? This these have to match. So this is 56 by 56. This also needs to be 56 by 56 in order to add them together. Remember, it's just simple element by element addition. Okay, simple matrix addition.
Benjamin Houghton: So they have to be the same size. And so if we're going to use a convolution operation in our network to go from.
Benjamin Houghton: say.
Benjamin Houghton: image sizes of 1 12 to say 56. Or then we need to. Also, the residual connection needs to be also down sample. And so they do that with this one by one convolution, with the sample, the stride of 2. Okay.
Benjamin Houghton: so that's how they they get around.
Benjamin Houghton: that issue of not being the same size. Okay? And then finally, alright. So here's an example. An example. 3. By 3. Convolution. 64 over 2. What does that mean? Means a 3 by 3 kernel with 64
Benjamin Houghton: 64 filters.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay,
Benjamin Houghton: a strive to strive to, for example, right? So that's the number of kernels, and that and filters in that chant in that layer. So or or so, if it has, guess if it has 64, input
Benjamin Houghton: 64 filters, it's gonna have 64 output channels. Right? So that's how you read this diagram, and then finally, the Ben, you'll see average pulling. And let's you know, let's take a closer
Benjamin Houghton: look at this real fast.
Benjamin Houghton: just so you can kind of zoom in on it, right? So you can see a little bit better here. But yeah, here's
Benjamin Houghton: you know, we have the input image which is going to be the same size as the Bgg. We do a 7 by 7 convolution.
Benjamin Houghton: What? 64 filters and a stride. Or, I'm sorry. Yeah stride of 2. Alright, then we do. Max pooling.
Benjamin Houghton: I think it's Max could be average pulling. Let's see, I think it's Max pooling
Benjamin Houghton: it. Just yeah, it is. Max Pooling says, right here, Max, pooling. Okay,
Benjamin Houghton: the stride of 2. So that actually cut the image size in half twice here. Actually, yeah, and you'll see. So it starts out at 2 24. When it comes out of this layer. It's going to be 1 12, and then it does the pooling, and it's gonna be 56,
Benjamin Houghton: right? So let's see.
Benjamin Houghton: let me see here.
Benjamin Houghton: Well, this would be 56, 2814, 7, right? Yeah. So
Benjamin Houghton: alright. So yeah, we start off at 2 24. We cut it in half. Now it's 1 12 after the orange after the orange layers, and then the purple layers. Now it's after that it's gonna be. I'm sorry it's gonna be 1 12 after orange. It's gonna be 56 after the pooling layer here that they snuck in.
Benjamin Houghton: and then it's gonna be 3.rd It's gonna be 28 after the purple layers. It's gonna be 14 after the green layer.
Benjamin Houghton: Now see, there's some something's not right here. Let's you know what? That's kind of confusing, isn't it? Let's take a look at this down here
Benjamin Houghton: 34 Layer associated the output size here.
Benjamin Houghton: they have the output size. Yeah. So
Benjamin Houghton: yeah. After those 7 by 7 we knew that it was going to be 1 12. And then after the okay. So I see. So what happens here is they? If you'll you'll notice that the purple layer does not have a convolution that directly down samples. So here the green layer has this divided by 2, which means stride 2, which cuts the image size in half, so they cut it in half here
Benjamin Houghton: to 1 12. They cut it in half, here to 56 and then. So now it's 56 and purple. It's 56 still 56, and then it comes to green and it gets cut in half. So now it's 28 gets cut in half here. So now it's 14 gets cut in half here. Now it's 7, and then they do what they do, a 7 by 7 average pooling here. And so the this output here 3 by 3 by 5, 12. If we look here, the output is 7 by 7,
Benjamin Houghton: and so you do a 7 by 7 average pooling and that converts the image from a 7 by 7 to a 1 by one image, actually, and
Benjamin Houghton: that is now it's flattened essentially. So you have 500. So the output size is going to be after you do the average pooling right? It's gonna be
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, they've got a couple of things smushed together here, actually, average pulling. You have 500.
Benjamin Houghton: Let's see.
Benjamin Houghton: Oh, yeah. But well, this is the 50 layer. Let's look at the 34 layer. Yeah, there's 512 channels right? And so. And the images are 7 by 7. So here we have
Benjamin Houghton: write it. We're gonna have 7.
Benjamin Houghton: See if I can get my pencil working here.
Benjamin Houghton: We're gonna have 7 by 7. 0, I almost broke my own rule.
Benjamin Houghton: We're gonna have 500 channels, 1, st 512 by 7 by 7. Okay? And so if we do a 7 by 7
Benjamin Houghton: average pooling, we just take the average of each channel. And so we'll have a vector that is dimensionality. Of what? What would it be then? It would be, and actually, for completeness sake, all right. And for number of samples in the batch.
Benjamin Houghton: So for batch size, this would be N by
Benjamin Houghton: 512 now. And and so now, we don't have this crazy vector, of like, what was it before? And
Benjamin Houghton: with Vgg like insane amount of like 25,000? It was 4 96. What is that number? Again? I don't
Benjamin Houghton: remember. It was like 3 by 3 by 5, 12, or something like that. What? What? We have it here?
Benjamin Houghton: It was 5, 12 by 7, by 7.
Benjamin Houghton: It's 25,000
Benjamin Houghton: the dimensionality is 25, it would be end by 25,000. This is much better. Number, right? Deal with 512. Okay, so we take that 512
Benjamin Houghton: dimensional vector plug it into a 1,000 fully connect layer of looks like, you know, an out would have a thousand input nodes or 1,000, whatever you want to say, a thousand nodes. That. Take these 512 inputs and gives you your 1,000
Benjamin Houghton: it'd be your output would be, and by 1,000 for your multi class classification task. And I bet you
Benjamin Houghton: I don't know if they list. The number of parameters in here, but
Benjamin Houghton: it's gotta be like significantly less
Benjamin Houghton: for the same number of layers, at least. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: I don't know. So anyways. Oh, here
Benjamin Houghton: parameters, Bgg, I mean, I don't know which version of res I know it, says Resident 32. But they have, like all these different versions like
Benjamin Houghton: they don't even have. This is for see that because they have, like different versions for different data sets. This is for Cfr, like they have an image net version,
Benjamin Houghton: smoothly decrease. Still our complexity.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, you see, right here, like we can remarkably, all of the depth is significantly increased. The 152 layer resnet.
Benjamin Houghton: 11.3 billion flops. It still has lower complexity than bg, like. So 152 layers versus, and a big part of that is
Benjamin Houghton: big. Part of that is the fully connected layer.
Benjamin Houghton: For sure that we, you know.
Benjamin Houghton: And you know, because we didn't really reduce the number of parameters we just introduced residual connections. Added more convolutional layers. And then.
Benjamin Houghton: you know, they're a little bit
Benjamin Houghton: more sophisticated, or I guess I'd say more modern approach to what we you know. This is what you see like you don't.
Benjamin Houghton: The flattening layer is is kind of is is kind of the old way of doing it. So anyways, we're gonna pause or stop the video here, it's getting kind of long, and we'll pick up in the next video.